Maddy: In this video we are going to look
at monitoring discipline and how can we
identify the interpersonal behaviour or
support the skills required by a manger.
Phillip: Your organisation should have
policies in place to guide you with resolving
disciplinary issues, so it is important that
you take time to familiarise yourself with them.
Maddy: Disciplinary issues at work are
usually to do with an employee’s conduct
or with their capability, or ability
to do their work to the right standard.
So what behaviours and skills do you need?
Phillip: There are interpersonal skills which can
be developed to help you monitor the discipline
in your team and in general it’s best to try and
resolve disciplinary issues informally at first,
if appropriate Having these skills can often help
avoid having to use formal mechanisms wherever
possible, but only when not deemed necessary.
Maddy: Coaching and mentoring are
great skills and behaviours to have
when it comes to capability issues.
Phillip: Coaching involves guiding someone
to help them achieve their goals and
potential and mentoring involves sharing
your knowledge, skills, and experience with
someone so they can develop their own skillset.
These are useful for dealing with issues
of capability, when the first action should
be to help them in achieving the expected
standard and not punish them for failing.
Maddy: Coaching and mentoring are powerful
tools in enabling personal professional
development and career development.
Personal professional development involves
assessing goals and aims, and the skills and
abilities needed to achieve them, and this covers
general life goals as well as career goals.
Phillip: Career development is similar,
though specifically focused on career goals.
Having the ability to coach and mentor
your team will not only help them through
capability issues but will also empower their
personal professional and career development.
Maddy: So how do we approach
difficult conversations?
When talking to people about conduct
and capability it can be tricky as
it touches on sensitive subjects.
Being able to have difficult conversations is an
important skill for team leaders and managers,
and there’s different methods for doing this.
Phillip: You should be calm and empathetic
during the conversation, making sure you
listen when the other person expresses their
feelings and point of view about the situation.
Be prepared by writing a list of key points
you want to cover, to stay on topic, also stick
to the facts as much as possible, rather than
being drawn into “She said/ He said” debates.
Keep the atmosphere positive and
focussed on fixing the situation,
rather than apportioning blame.
Maddy: Provide clear feedback is often
related to difficult conversations
but is also a skill, in its own right.
When giving someone feedback about their
conduct or performance, that feedback should
be precise and not open to misinterpretation.
Try to stick to the facts as much as
possible, even using data if its available.
Also think about what’s the best
way to give someone feedback if
it’s about something sensitive.
Better to do it in person rather than by email.
Phillip: Organisational skills
As a team leader, you’re responsible for making
sure your team stays organised and efficient.
Workplace conflicts that lead to
disciplinary issues are often caused
by teams being poorly organised.
By taking steps to make sure your team
is well organised; everyone has a clearly
defined job role, there are strong lines of
communication, and people understand the goals
they’re expected to achieve; your team will
be much less prone to disciplinary issues.
Maddy: Spend time each day thinking about how
your team are going to achieve their tasks.
What problems can you anticipate?
What’s gone right or wrong before?
Doing small things like making ‘To Do lists’
is a great way of staying better organised
and the more organised you are, the better
the example you’re setting for your team.
Phillip: Empathy
Disciplinary issues often
have an emotional component.
The standard of someone’s work may have
declined because of emotional trouble or
their conduct may be inappropriate because of
other frustrations elsewhere in their life.
Maddy: When responding to disciplinary issues,
try putting yourself in the other person’s shoes.
Showing understanding of what it feels like
to be the other person and their situation
can help you gauge the right response and
help to figure out why it’s happening.
Phillip: Being more empathetic and understanding
the feeling of others can make you a more
observant and approachable team leader.
This also enables your team to feel you are
more approachable and can help make disciplinary
issues less likely to occur and escalate.
Maddy: Safeguarding
Disciplinary issues can also be due to complicated
causes that are not under the person’s control.
These may be inside or outside of work.
By investigating what’s going on, you might
find that there are safeguarding issues.
Phillip: These can occur when someone is
judged to be vulnerable due to age, disability,
illness, or an inability to protect themselves
from abuse or communicate abuse appears to
be or actually is suffering abuse or neglect.
If there are members of your team who are
considered vulnerable adults, you should be
especially mindful of their status, if there
are disciplinary issues involving them, as
this could be a sign of safeguarding issues.
Maddy: You should immediately escalate this to HR
and to law enforcement or other external bodies,
if necessary, especially if there is reason
to believe there is physical or sexual abuse.
You can be prosecuted for failing in
your safeguarding duties, so it is
important to treat this very seriously.